Rizqy Amelia Zein

Curriculum Vitae

PhD Student Email: Amelia. Zein@psy.lmu.de

Department of Psychology Web: http://rameliaz.github.io

Ludwig Maxmillians Universität Codes: http://github.com/rameliaz

Leopoldstr. 13

80802 München, Germany

Assistant Professor (on a study leave) Email: amelia.zein@psikologi.unair.ac.id

Department of Psychology Universitas Airlangga

Kampus B UNAIR Jalan Airlangga 4-6 Surabaya

Jawa Timur, Indonesia 60286

Introduction

My PhD project focuses on understanding how people relate to scientific and religious explanations. I'm broadly interested in researching health misinformation, conspiracy beliefs, and public attitudes to science. I'm also very passionate about research methods, metascience, computational reproducibility, psychometrics, and latent variable modeling.

Academic Positions

Since 2018	Assistant Professor (Tenured Civil Servant)	Universitas Airlangga
2015 – 2018	Assistant Professor (Probationary Civil Servant)	Universitas Airlangga
2011 – 2015	Temporary Tutor	Universitas Airlangga

Education

Since 2021	PhD in Social Psychology (Dr. phil.), Fakultäten für Psychologie und Pädagogik.	Ludwig-Maxmillians-Universität, München, Germany
	Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Mario Gollwitzer	, , , , , , , , , , , , , , , , , , , ,
2012 – 2013	Master of Science (M.Sc.) in Social Research	University of Edinburgh, United
	School of Social and Political Science	Kingdom
	Supervisor: Ross Bond	
2007 – 2011	Sarjana Psikologi (S.Psi.)	Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya,
	Faculty of Psychology	Indonesia
	Supervisor: Ilham Nur Alfian	

Awards, Honors, and Scholarship

2021	Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst (DAAD), Programm Forschungsstipendien -
	Promotionen in Deutschland
2016-2018	Dean Award of Teaching Excellence
2012	Unggulan Scholarship (Master), Indonesian Ministry of Education and Culture
2010	3 rd place of Singgih Dirga Gunarsa Award (student category)

2024	Research	Open Science of Religion. The John Templeton Foundation. <i>Measuring How Individuals Relate Science to Religion</i> . \$21.000. Role: PI
2021	Travel	Attending Aspen Global Congress on Scientific Thinking and Action The Aspen Institute Science and Society Program. Rome, 17-20 March 2021.
2020	Research	Data Collection Grant; Institute for Future Studies (IFFS) Sweden. International
		Study of Norms Violations during Coronavirus Pandemic. 1000€. Role: Research Collaborator.
2020	Research	42/UN3.1.9/2020; Universitas Airlangga ECR Grant. <i>Health Misinformation, Vaccine Hesitancy, and Religiosity: A Meta-Analysis Study.</i> Rp25.000.000. Role: Collaborator.
2019	Travel	Attending Triangle Scholarly Communication Institute (TriangleSCI), Durham (NC), 13-17 October 2019.
2019	Travel	Attending SIPS Pre-Conference RepliCATS workshop, Rotterdam, 6-7 July 2019
2019	Research	Data Collection Grant; Institute for Future Studies (IFFS) Sweden. International

Study of Meta-Norms. 1000€. Role: Research Collaborator.

Rp25.000.000. Role: PI

Role: PI

886/UN3/2018; Universitas Airlangga ECR Grant. *Protecting those who care:*Comparing subjective and actual risk of contracting lung TB in healthcare workers.

39/UN3.1.9/2017; Faculty of Psychology Universitas Airlangga ECR Grant. Do

justice and trust matter to supporting social health insurance policy? Rp25.000.000.

Scientific Contributions

Grants

2018

2017

Peer-reviewed journal articles

Research

Research

- 1. **Zein, R. A.**, Heene, M., & Gollwitzer, M. (2024). Stage 1 Registered Report: Measuring How Individuals Relate Science to Religion. *The International Journal for the Psychology of Religion* [in-principal acceptance].
- 2. **Zein, R. A.**, Altenmüller, M. S., & Gollwitzer, M. (2024). Longtime nemeses or cordial allies? How individuals mentally relate science and religion. *Psychological Review*, *Advance online publication*. https://doi.org/10.1037/rev0000492
- 3. **Zein, R. A.**, Wulandari, R. D., Ridlo, I. A., Hendriani, W., Suhariadi, F., & Rianto, A. (2022). The characteristics of occupational Tuberculosis risk in health care workers. *International Journal of Health Planning and Management*, *37*(5), 2669-2683. https://doi.org/10.1002/hpm.3489
- 4. **Zein, R. A.**, Putri, N. K., & Ridlo, I. A. (2020). Do justice and trust affect acceptability of Indonesian social health insurance policy? *International Journal of Health Governance*, *25*(1), 78-92. https://doi.org/10.1108/IJHG-05-2019-0028
- 5. **Zein, R. A.** (2018). 'Is Ethnicity the Root of all Evil?' Engaging Macro and Micro Analysis of Ethnic Violence in Post New-order Indonesia. *Politik Indonesia: Indonesian Political Science Review*, 3(2), 262–279. https://doi.org/10.15294/ipsr.v3i2.13985
- 6. **Zein, R. A.**, & Alfian, I. N. (2018). Faktor Determinan Perilaku Konservasi Energi dalam Skala Rumah Tangga dan Sektor Transportasi pada Konsumen Produk Elektronik Ramah Lingkungan dan BBM Non-Subsidi. *Jurnal Psikologi*, *45*(3), 231. https://doi.org/10.22146/jpsi.10818
- Zein, R. A. (2018). What's the matter with being Indonesian? A social representation approach to unravelling Indonesian national identity / ¿Qué significa ser indonesio? Una perspectiva de la representación social para desentrañar la identidad nacional indonesia. *Revista de Psicologia* Social, 33(2), 390–423. https://doi.org/10.1080/02134748.2018.1435219

8. **Zein, R. A.**, Suhariadi, F., & Hendriani, W. (2017). Estimating the effect of lay knowledge and prior contact with pulmonary TB patients, on health-belief model in a high-risk pulmonary TB transmission population. *Psychology Research and Behavior Management*, *Volume 10*, 187–194. https://doi.org/10.2147/PRBM.S134034

Collaborations

- 1. Andersson, P. A., Vartanova, I., [...], **Zein, R. A.**, [....], & Eriksson, K. (2024). Anger and disgust shape judgments of social sanctions across cultures, especially in high individual autonomy societies. Scientific reports, 14(1), 5591. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-55815-x
- 2. Andrighetto, G., Szekely, A., [...], **Zein, R. A.**, [...], & Eriksson, K. (2024). Changes in social norms during the early stages of the COVID-19 pandemic across 43 countries. *Nature Communications*, 15(1), 1436. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-44999-5
- Gollwitzer, M., Prager, J., Altenmüller, M. S., & Zein, R. A. (2023). Simplification Is Not Indoctrination. *Psychology Learning & Teaching*, 22(3), 245-250. https://doi.org/10.1177/14757257231195352
- 4. Onie, S., Vina, A., [...], **Zein, R. A.,** [...], & Larsen, M. E. (2023). Indonesian first national suicide prevention strategy: key findings from the qualitative situational analysis. *The Lancet Regional Health-Southeast Asia*, 16. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lansea.2023.100245
- Terry, J., [...], Zein, R. A., [...], & Field, A. (2023). Data from an International Multi-Centre Study of Statistics and Mathematics Anxieties and Related Variables in University Students (the SMARVUS Dataset). Journal of Open Psychology Data, 11(1), Article 8. https://doi.org/10.5334/jopd.80
- McLamore, Q., [...] & Zein, R. A. (2023). The distinct associations of ingroup attachment and glorification with responses to the coronavirus pandemic: Evidence from a multilevel investigation in 21 countries. *British Journal of Social Psychology*, 62(2), 992-1012. https://doi.org/10.1111/bjso.12614
- 7. Bago, B., [...], **Zein, R. A.**, [...], Hoekstra, R., & Aczel, B. (2022). Situational factors shape moral judgements in the trolley dilemma in Eastern, Southern and Western countries in a culturally diverse sample. *Nature Human Behaviour*. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-022-01319-5
- 8. McLamore, Q., [...], **Zein, R. A.**, [...], Yeung, W. L. V., & Burrows, B. (2022). Trust in scientific information mediates associations between conservatism and coronavirus responses in the U.S., but few other nations. *Scientific Reports*, *12*, 3724. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-07508-6
- 9. Eriksson, K., [...], **Zein, R. A.**, [...], Zirganou-Kazolea, L., & Van Lange, P. (2021). Perceptions of the appropriate response to norm violation in 57 societies. *Nature Communication*, *12*(1), 1-11. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-21602-9
- 10. Irawan, D. E., Abraham, J., **Zein, R. A.**, Ridlo, I. A., & Aribowo, E. K. (2021). Open access in Indonesia. *Development and Change*, *52*, 651-660. https://doi.org/10.1111/dech.12637
- Maison, D., Marchlewska, M., Zein, R. A., Syarifah, D., & Purba, H. (2019). Religiously permissible consumption: The influence of the halal label on product perceptions depending on the centrality of religiosity. *Journal of Islamic Marketing*, 10(3), 948–960. https://doi.org/10.1108/JIMA-07-2018-0119
- Ridlo, I. A., & Zein, R. A. (2018). #CondomEmoji: Are urban Indonesians receptive to a social media-based campaign for safer sex? *Health Education*, 118(5), 386–401. https://doi.org/10.1108/HE-02-2018-0010
- 13. Ridlo, I. A., & **Zein, R. A.** (2018). Arah Kebijakan Kesehatan Mental: Tren Global dan Nasional Serta Tantangan Aktual. *Buletin Penelitian Kesehatan*, *46*(1), 45–52.

https://doi.org/10.22435/bpk.v46i1.56

- Maison, D., Marchlewska, M., Syarifah, D., Zein, R. A., & Purba, H. P. (2018). Explicit versus implicit "Halal" information: Influence of the halal label and the country-of-origin information on product perceptions in Indonesia. Frontiers in Psychology, 9(MAR), 1–7. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyq.2018.00382
- 15. Dewi, T. K., & **Zein, R. A.** (2017). Predicting Intention to Perform Breast Self-Examination: Application of the Theory of Reasoned Action. *Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention*, *11*. https://doi.org/10.22034/APJCP.2017.18.11.2945
- Fajrianthi, F., & Zein, R. A. (2017). Development of a psychological test to measure ability-based emotional intelligence in the Indonesian workplace using an item response theory. *Psychology Research and Behavior Management, Volume 10*, 339–352. https://doi.org/10.2147/PRBM.S143113
- 17. Suhariadi, F., **Zein, R. A.**, Alfian, I. N., & Hadi, C. (2016). The Tale of Seeking Treatment: A Qualitative Study of Pulmonary Tuberculosis Patients. *Psychology, Community & Health*, *5*(3), 229–243. https://doi.org/10.5964/pch.v5i3.152

Book Chapter

Zein, R. A. (2021). Metode Penelitian dalam Psikologi Politik. In W. Yustisia, M. A. Hakim, & R. Ardi (Ed.), *Psikologi politik* (pp. 33-74). Jakarta: Penerbit Buku Kompas. Preprint: https://rinarxiv.lipi.go.id/lipi/preprint/view/773

Preprints

Zein, R. A., Arinda, M. F., Rikardi, A., Ardelia, V., & Ridlo, I. A. (2020). The enemy of 'ummah: Belief in Jewish conspiracy theories indirectly affected vaccination decisions. *PsyArXiv*. https://doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/53qsk.

Selected non-peer-reviewed writings & op-eds

- 1. **Zein, R.A.** (2024). Mengenal cara kerja 'paper mill': pabrik artikel ilmiah yang beroperasi seperti kartel di film-film. The Conversation Indonesia.
- 2. **Zein, R.A.** (2021). Open science can help accelerate and protect high-quality research in low-income countries. *The Conversation France.*
- 3. **Zein, R.A.** (2021). 27% penduduk Indonesia masih ragu terhadap vaksin COVID-19, mengapa penting meyakinkan mereka. *The Conversation Indonesia.*
- 4. Irawan, D.E., Abraham, J., **Zein, R.A.**, & Gutham, S. (2020). India's plan to pay journal subscription fees for all its citizen may end up making science harder to access. *The Conversation Indonesia*.
- 5. **Zein, R. A.** (2019). Prabowo Tak Percaya Hasil Hitung Cepat: Mengapa partisan berpikir konspiratif? *The Conversation Indonesia*.

Collaborative multi-national projects

1. 2022 University of Michigan, United States (US). *Cross-Cultural Disgust Perception Project.* PI: Joshua Ackerman, Daniel M. T. Fessler, & Thomas Kupfer.

- 2021 University of Sussex, United Kingdom (UK). The convergent and discriminant validity of maths anxiety and statistics anxiety: A multi-site, multi-study project. PI: Prof. Andy Field and Jenny Terry (University of Sussex, Brighton, UK).
- 3. 2020 Institute for Future Studies (IFFS) Sweden. International Study of Norms Violations during Coronavirus Pandemic. Pl: Dr. Giulia Andrighetto (Institute of Cognitive Sciences and Technology, Italy).
- 2020 Psychological Science Accelerator (PSA). Moral thinking across the world: Exploring the 4. influence of personal force and intention in moral dilemma judgements. [Accepted 1st stage registered report in Nature Human Behavior). Pl: Dr. Balasz Aczel (ELTE University, Hungary).
- University of Massachusetts, Amherst. The persuasiveness of strategic science 5. 2020 communication on compliance with scientific recommendations across Nations during the COVID-19 pandemic. Pl: Dr. Bernhard Leidner (UMass, Amherst).
- Institute for Future Studies (IFFS) Sweden. International Study of Meta-Norms. Pl: Dr. 6. 2019 Kimmo Eriksson (University of Stockholm).

Professional Community Services

Ad-hoc peer-review

Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies (x2), PLoS ONE (x6), Social Justice Research (2x), Psychology and Sexuality (x1), Psychology Research and Behavior Management (x1), Jurnal Berkala Epidemiologi (x1), MAKARA Human Behavior Studies in Asia (x1), Journal of Social Psychology (x3), International Quarterly of Community Health Education (1x), Public Understanding of Science (2x), International Journal of Psychology (1x).

Others

2019	Committee, 36th Anniversary of Faculty of Psychology
2019	Committee, Webinar Sains – Advancing Science in Indonesia: Current Global Research
	Practices
2019-present	Member/Co-Founder, Sains Terbuka Airlangga (https://sainsterbukaua.github.io/)
2019-present	Researcher-in-training, Institute for Globally Distributed Open Research and Education
	(IGDORE)
2019-2020	Volunteer, INArxiv pre-print server
2016-2021	Editor-in-chief, INSAN Jurnal Psikologi dan Kesehatan Mental

Presentations

Invited talk

08/07/2023	Komunikasi Kesarjanaan dalam Bidang Sosial Humaniora, Persatuan Pelajar Indonesia (PPI) Jerman
11/12/2022	Proses Psikologis dalam Pengalaman Ketidakadilan, BEM Fakultas Psikologi Universitas Airlangga – Konferensi Mahasiswa Merdeka Belajar (KMMB)
12/10/2022	Perkembangan Kajian Psikologi Moral Secara Global dan di Indonesia, Fakultas Psikologi Universitas Muhammadiyah Prof. Dr. HAMKA dan Ikatan Psikologi Sosial
01/10/2022	Menulis Pembahasan dan Abstrak dalam Artikel Ilmiah, Pusat Kajian Psikologi Komunikasi dan Budaya (PUSKALOKA) dan SUKSMA: Jurnal Psikologi Universitas Sanata Dharma Yogyakarta

14/09/2022	Internasionalisasi, Pemeringkatan, dan Integritas Akademik di Universitas, Fakultas Keguruan dan Ilmu Pendidikan (FKIP) Universitas Muhammadiyah Prof. Dr. HAMKA
27/08/2020	Mengelola Pembelajaran Jarak-Jauh dengan Online Delivery , Fakultas Psikologi Universitas Airlangga
08/08/2020	Penolakan Vaksin, Kepercayaan Konspiratif, dan Bagaimana Menyikapinya, Webinar Series: Ilmuwan Merespon Pandemi, <i>Society of Indonesian Science Journalists</i> (SISJ) & Akademi Ilmuwan Muda Indonesia (ALMI)
05/04/2020	Sintesis Pengetahuan dengan Meninjau Literatur, Department of Health Policy and Administration Universitas Airlangga
21/09/2019	Menulis Artikel Opini dan Komunikasi Sains, Kelas Literasi Klub Seri Buku
08/08/2019	Menulis Artikel Populer dari Karya Ilmiah, Direktorat Sistem Informasi (DSI) Universitas Airlangga
07/23/2019	Self-Archiving, The Conversation Indonesia Writing Workshop
19/07/2019	Self-Archiving and Introduction to Open Science , The Indonesian Journal of Health Administration Workshop
25/04/2019	Encouraging Academics to Embrace #OpenScience, The 5th UGM Public Health Symposium
21/01/2019	Challenging Religious Extremism: Social Psychology Perspective, Universitas Nahdlatul 'Ulama Surabaya

Workshops

30/01/2020	Confirmatory Factor Analysis, Faculty of Education Universitas Negeri Semarang
22-23/11/2019	Multigroup Structural Equation Modeling, Faculty of Psychology Universitas Airlangga
02/11/2019	Multilevel Modeling/Linear Mixed Effect, Faculty of Psychology Universitas Islam Sultan
	Agung, Semarang
04/09/2019	Multilevel Modeling/Linear Mixed Effect, Faculty of Psychology Universitas Airlangga
05/10/2018	Statistical Power Workshop, Faculty of Psychology Universitas Airlangga

Professional Development

Workshops

18/08/2020	Good Clinical Practice, NDA Clinical Trials Network
01/11/2018	Multilevel Modeling, Indonesian Association of Social Psychology (IPS)
14/12/2017	Psychological Test Adaptation, HIMPSI Jawa Timur
20/11/2017	Basic and Advanced Training on Bioethics, Faculty of Public Health Universitas
	Airlangga
10-21/04/2017	Applied Approach, Universitas Airlangga
06-10/03/2017	PEKERTI, Universitas Airlangga
24/07 - 6/12/2017	Pelatihan Dasar Calon PNS Golongan III, Pusdiklat Kementerian Pendidikan dan
	Kebudayaan

MOOCs

23/10/2019	Improving your statistical questions, TU Eindhoven, Coursera
01/02/2019	Improving your statistical inferences, TU Eindhoven, Coursera
03/04/2018	Inferential statistics, University of Amsterdam, Coursera

Summer School

07/03/2013 Advanced Issues in Survey Design and Analysis, Utrecht University

Professional Membership

2020-present Society of Indonesian Science Journalists (SISJ)
2013-present Indonesian Association of Social Psychology (IPS)

Skills

Language

Native Bahasa Jawa
Native Bahasa Indonesia
C1 English, IELTS 7.5 (2020, Listening 8.0, Reading 8.5, Writing 6.5, & Speaking 7.5)
B1 German
A1 Japanese

Methodology/Statistics

Latent Variable Modeling (proficient)

Latent Response Model (working knowledge)

Multilevel Modeling/Linear Mixed Effect (working knowledge)

General Linear Models (working knowledge)

Generalized Linear Models (working knowledge)

Systematic Review (working knowledge)

Meta-Analysis (working knowledge)

Directed Acyclic Graph (DAG) (beginner)

Network Modeling (beginner)

Statistical Programming, Data Analysis, Survey Programming, & Publishing Tools

SPSS, JASP, & jamovi (proficient)

R (working knowledge)

HTML (working knowledge)

PHP (working knowledge)

Excel (working knowledge)

Git (working knowledge)

Mplus (working knowledge)

Sosci Survey, Survey Monkey, LimeSurvey, & Qualtrics (working knowledge)

R Markdown & Quarto (working knowledge)

MySQL (beginner) formr (beginner) lab.js (beginner)

Mentorship

2021	Riezky Putra Santoso, undergraduate thesis
2021	Faza Izzudin Nuha, undergraduate thesis
2021	Fiona Fira Winata, undergraduate thesis
2020	Naufal A. Farisy, undergraduate thesis
2020	Sita Nadia Salsabilla Widodo, undergraduate thesis
2020	Hibatullah Anfal Farisi, undergraduate thesis
2020	Maghfira Fahmi Arinda, undergraduate thesis
2020	Audi Ahmad Rikardi, undergraduate thesis

Teaching

Odd Semester PSK301 Community Mental Health

2020/2021 PSA212 Community Assessment and Intervention

PSU108 Personality Psychology (Regular Programme) PSU108 Personality Psychology (IUP/AMERTA)

PHP101 Philosophy of Science (IUP)

PSS405 Social Psychology Seminar

Even Semester PNP206 Quantitative Research Methods and Data Analysis

2020/2021 PSS104 Social Cognition (Regular Programme)

PSS104 Social Cognition (IUP/AMERTA)

PNP206 Quantitative Research Methods (Master of Professional Psychology)

MAS702 Advanced Statistics (Master of Professional Psychology)

PSS405 Social Psychology Seminar

For assigned courses from 2020 backwards, please refer to PDDikti database.

Last updated: 17 July 2024
http://rameliaz.github.io/files/cv